<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>TidyBlocks Blog</title>
  <link href="https://tidyblocks.tech/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://tidyblocks.tech"/>
  <updated>2020-07-28T12:00:00</updated>
  <id>https://tidyblocks.tech</id>
  <author>
    <name>The TidyBlocks Team</name>
    <email>info@tidyblocks.tech</email>
  </author>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Other Ninety Percent</title>
    <link href="https://tidyblocks.tech/blog/2020/08/28/the-other-ninety-percent/"/>
    <updated>2020-08-28T12:00:00</updated>
    <id>https://tidyblocks.tech/blog/2020/08/28/the-other-ninety-percent/</id>
    <content type="html">We made several improvements to TidyBlocks this week,
but not all of them are visible to users.
The ones that are include:

More of the interface has been translated.
We now have a block for calculating running sums and averages.
And there is another new block for shifting columns up and down
so that users can...</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>And Now for Some Statistics</title>
    <link href="https://tidyblocks.tech/blog/2020/08/15/and-now-for-some-statistics/"/>
    <updated>2020-08-15T12:00:00</updated>
    <id>https://tidyblocks.tech/blog/2020/08/15/and-now-for-some-statistics/</id>
    <content type="html">It has been another busy week for TidyBlocks:
we have a beautiful new layout courtesy of Maya Gans,
we can download SVG versions of all our blocks at once thanks to Justin Singh,
and we have a new Twitter account @tidyblocks.
We have also started to add more statistical blocks
so that people can use...</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Hippocratic License</title>
    <link href="https://tidyblocks.tech/blog/2020/08/14/hippocratic-license/"/>
    <updated>2020-08-14T12:00:00</updated>
    <id>https://tidyblocks.tech/blog/2020/08/14/hippocratic-license/</id>
    <content type="html">Over the past few years,
more and more people have become concerned with
the ethical implications of work in data science and machine learning.
From algorithmic bias to facial recognition,
the tools we teach people to build and use have the potential to do great harm;
as teachers,
we have a responsibility to make our students...</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>TidyBlocks Meets React</title>
    <link href="https://tidyblocks.tech/blog/2020/08/02/react/"/>
    <updated>2020-08-02T13:00:00</updated>
    <id>https://tidyblocks.tech/blog/2020/08/02/react/</id>
    <content type="html">TidyBlocks was originally developed as purely a JavaScript application, which
made it difficult to really modify and customize the UI. When it came time to give
things a fresh coat of paint we decided to build it using React for three main reasons:


Components. We'd be able to take advantage of the React...</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Creating a Block</title>
    <link href="https://tidyblocks.tech/blog/2020/08/02/creating-a-block/"/>
    <updated>2020-08-02T12:00:00</updated>
    <id>https://tidyblocks.tech/blog/2020/08/02/creating-a-block/</id>
    <content type="html">We love collaborators and welcome any PRs with new block ideas,
so this developer tutorial will walk you through creating your own statistical block.
All TidyBlocks blocks have three parts, which we will look at in turn:

The block UI: what the block looks like and what fields it includes
The generator code: how...</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Structure</title>
    <link href="https://tidyblocks.tech/blog/2020/07/28/structure/"/>
    <updated>2020-07-28T12:00:00</updated>
    <id>https://tidyblocks.tech/blog/2020/07/28/structure/</id>
    <content type="html">The structure of the code in TidyBlocks is dictated by three things:

The architecture of Blockly.
Our experience generating JavaScript directly from blocks.
Our desire to write comprehensive unit tests.

Rather than describing these at a high level,
let's have a look at a simple pipeline that loads a data set,
filters it,
and generates a plot:

...</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Questions About TidyBlocks</title>
    <link href="https://tidyblocks.tech/blog/2020/07/27/questions-about-tidyblocks/"/>
    <updated>2020-07-27T12:00:00</updated>
    <id>https://tidyblocks.tech/blog/2020/07/27/questions-about-tidyblocks/</id>
    <content type="html">Our first post described the history of TidyBlocks so far.
In this post we'd like to answer a few of the questions people have asked.
Is TidyBlocks an RStudio product?
No.
The first version was developed by Maya Gans while she was a summer intern,
but TidyBlocks is a free-standing open source project.
Does TidyBlocks use...</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Project History</title>
    <link href="https://tidyblocks.tech/blog/2020/07/26/project-history/"/>
    <updated>2020-07-26T12:00:00</updated>
    <id>https://tidyblocks.tech/blog/2020/07/26/project-history/</id>
    <content type="html">TidyBlocks officially started in May 2019,
but its roots go back to the creation of Scratch in the early 2000s,
and beyond that to the programming language Logo designed in the late 1960s.
Both use turtle graphics to make programming more accessible,
but Scratch went further by allowing people to build programs by clicking...</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
